Guide to the Children's Hospital at Stanford Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Children's Hospital at Stanford records
1917-1977
SC0297
Children's Hospital at Stanford.
6.5 Linear feet
These records were collected by Ruth Spande Atwood, first superintentdent and administrator of the Stanford Convalescent Home (1923-1961), and include correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings and photographs. Subjects include the history of the Home, individuals who served on Boards and assisted with fund raising, and patients. Of note are the photographs and letters of Sam McDonald. Other correspondents include Dr. Esther Clark, Dr. William F. Durand, Dr. Harold Faber, Timothy Hopkins, Ray Lyman Wilbur, and the artist Wolo (Wolo Trutzschler von Falkenstein). Collection also includes a Memory Book (1917-1977) and Scrapbook (1928-1961) largely containing photographs, with some articles and programs, on the Home, its staff and patients, special events, the artist Wolo and his murals, Ruth Spande Atwood, Sam McDonald, and Dr. David Charles Gardner.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Paul W. Atwood, 1983.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Originally the Stanford Convalescent Home, established on the Stanford campus in 1919 for needy children with long term illness, this privately supported organization changed its name to the Children's Hospital at Stanford in 1970.
Description of the Collection
These records were collected by Ruth Spande Atwood, first superintentdent and administrator of the Stanford Convalescent Home (1923-1961), and include correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings and photographs. Subjects include the history of the Home, individuals who served on Boards and assisted with fund raising, and patients. Of note are the photographs and letters of Sam McDonald. Other correspondents include Dr. Esther Clark, Dr. William F. Durand, Dr. Harold Faber, Timothy Hopkins, Ray Lyman Wilbur, and the artist Wolo (Wolo Trutzschler von Falkenstein). Collection also includes a Memory Book (1917-1977) and Scrapbook (1928-1961) largely containing photographs, with some articles and programs, on the Home, its staff and patients, special events, the artist Wolo and his murals, Ruth Spande Atwood, Sam McDonald, and Dr. David Charles Gardner.
Access Terms
Atwood, Ruth Spande.; Children's Hospital at Stanford.; Clark, Esther Bridgman.; Durand, William Frederick, 1859-1958; Faber, Harold Kniest, 1884-1979.; Gardner, David Charles.; Hopkins, Timothy, 1859-1937.; MacDonald, Emanuel B.; Stanford Home for Convalescent Children.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Wolo, d. 1989.; Children --Health and hygiene.; Children --Hospitals --California.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - Shirley Temple Black 1956-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Convalescent Home Forms (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Student Nurse Program 1932-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medical Staff 1954-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Some Board Members 1944-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Some Celebrities 1954-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dr. William F. Durand 1930-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Harold Faber 1923-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Charles Gardner 1920-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Herbert Hoover 1932-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Timothy Hopkins 1926-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ira S. Lillick 1931-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - J. Pearce Mitchell 1928-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stanford Convalescent Home (SCH) History 1919-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters from children (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proposal for SCH Medical and Rehabilitation Center 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photos of children (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Radio, TV, Films 1933-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Christmas cards (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stories about children (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Patient’s families 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - SCH School 1940-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scouting (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Staff 1923-1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Superintendent’s reports 1924-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - SCH Newspaper reports 1926-1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ruth Spande Atwood: Career and Personal 1920-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stanford School of Nursing (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photos of the Convalescent Home (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - White House Conference 1931 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Professional Associations (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ruth Atwood in retirement 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Happy Birthday cards from children to Ruth Atwood (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Christmas cards from children to Ruth Atwood 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Christmas cards from children to Ruth Atwood 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Foreign hospital visits (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Stanford family campus home (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stanford University 1932-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Medical School 1933-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Stanford area news, folder 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stanford area news, folder 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - SCH Senior Auxiliary 1919-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - SCH Palo Alto Junior Auxiliary & Allied Arts Guild (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - SCH San Francisco Junior Auxiliary (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - SCH Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Wolo, SCH muralist (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Con Home week 1929-1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sam McDonald (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1956 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1957 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1959 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1960 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Program to the Woodside-Atherton Junior Auxiliary Horse Show 1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Program to the San Francisco Junior Auxiliary Dance 1962 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Oversize letters by Wolo (removed from Box 5, folder 1) (Box 6 os)
  - Resolution to Mrs. Atwood on her [65th] birthday and announcement of presentation of The Ruth Spande Atwood Endowment Fund [hand-lettered, 4/24/61] (Box 6)
  - Photos:
    - New Administration building dedication 1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Drawing of new Administration building (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Mrs. Timothy Hopkins 1935 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Original painting by Wolo (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ruth Spande Atwood 1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified man (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - A Stanford Convalescent Hospital ward (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Memory Book, pages 1-5 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Memory Book, pages 6-10 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Memory Book, pages 11-15 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Memory Book, pages 16-20 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Memory Book, pages 21-25 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Memory Book, pages 26-30 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Memory Book, pages 31-35 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Memory Book, pages 36-40 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Memory Book, pages 41-45 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Memory Book, pages 46-50 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Memory Book, pages 51-56 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Memory Book, original covers (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 4-5 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 6-7 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 10, 11, 12 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 13 (David Charles Gardner, Dr. Esther Clark) (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 17, 20 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 21 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 26-27 (the Home’s buildings) (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 28, 30 (David Charles Gardner) (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 31 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 33 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 34 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 35 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 36, 38, 39 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 40-41 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 44, 46, 49, 50 (artist Wolo) (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook photos from page 51 (Wolo’s murals) (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 52,55, 56, 57 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 69, 71 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 72, 75, 76, 77 (Sam McDonald) (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook photos from pages 80, 81, 82, 84 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook (photographs, clippings, articles) 1928-1961 (Box 8 os)
  - Annual Reports 1917-1960 (4 bound volumes) (Box 9)